<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Considerations tending to remove the present differences, and to settle vnity, peace, and piety for the present and future. Written from the Sommer Islands by R. Norvvood. And sent over to further the reconciliation of his native country.</title>
            <author>Norwood, Richard, 1590?-1675.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89754</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N1378</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E366_5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201257</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861785</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861785</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113930</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89754)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113930)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 59:E366[5])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Considerations tending to remove the present differences, and to settle vnity, peace, and piety for the present and future. Written from the Sommer Islands by R. Norvvood. And sent over to further the reconciliation of his native country.</title>
                  <author>Norwood, Richard, 1590?-1675.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.M. for M. Spark, and are to be sold at the sign of the Blue Bible in Green Arbour.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Dec: 16".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church and state --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113930:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CONSIDERATIONS tending To remove the preſent Differences, AND To ſettle <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, Peace,</hi> and <hi>Piety</hi> for the preſent and future.</p>
            <p>Written from the Sommer Iſlands By R. NORVVOOD.</p>
            <p>And ſent over to further the Reconciliation of his Native COUNTRY.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. M.</hi> for <hi>M. Spark,</hi> and are to be ſold at the ſign of the Blue Bible in Green Arbour. 1646.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:113930:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:113930:2"/>
            <head>CONSIDERATIONS <hi>tending</hi> To remove the preſent differences, <hi>AND</hi> To ſettle <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, Peace, and Piety, For the preſent and future.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE great diſtractions and diſſentions in our dear Native Country, and other places thereon depending, muſt needs be very grievous to every Chriſtian heart: And if it pleaſe the Lord to diſcover to any man a likely way of reconcilement by juſt and good means, he may not through ſlothful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſ, or timerouſneſſ conceal it, leſt he incur that heavy ſentence pronounced againſt the unprofitable ſervant, that hid his maſters talent in the ground.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ground and cauſe of the preſent diſſentions, and troubles ſeems to be this, That men have been accuſtomed, and do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that Magiſterial rule and Government in a Chriſtian Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth is of two kinds or ſorts; namely, Civil and Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical, the one not ſubordinate to the other, or how ſubordinate to the other, and how not? And this ſeems to have been a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal ground and cauſe of diſcord in the Church, in all ages, ſince Chriſt.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:113930:3"/>
            <p n="3">3. This pretended Eccleſiaſtical Magiſtracy, as it differs from Chriſtian Magiſtracy called Civil, hath, in all ages, been aſſumed by the Clergy, in ſome degree: And its like it began to work and ſhew it ſelf even in the Apoſtles times in the opinions and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of men in ſome meaſure; becauſe the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of iniquity doth already work;</hi> yet it appeared more evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and eminent, when whole Kingdomes and Commonweales embraced the Chriſtian Faith, eſpecially when the whole Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire embraced it. For then Princes, Kings, and Emperors, and their Republiques, out of a pious ignorance, or rather an ignorant piouſneſs did condeſcent to grant this to the Clergy, in ſome large meaſure, which they claimed by divine right to belong un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them: and its like they uſed it moderately at firſt, but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards did by it ſubjugate all other Magiſtracy; and ſuch is the nature of it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Now that this pretended Eccleſiaſtical Magiſtracy, aſſumed by the Clergy, was the thing which the Apoſtle ſpeaks of (2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 27. when he ſaith <hi>The myſtery of iniquity doth already work: on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he which now withholdeth ſhal let, til he be taken out of the way</hi>) may appear, becauſe he intimates that the Emperor and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy did hinder that myſtery of iniquity from taking place; For they would doubtleſſe have been no hinderers of the Apoſtacy, I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry, and other Errors accompanying this myſtery from taking place; therefore it muſt be this which they were hinderers of: And then it will follow that this is it which the Apoſtle cals <hi>the myſtery of iniquity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. And this Eccleſiaſtical Magiſtracy, aſſumed by the Clergy, remains the ſame in ſubſtance, though the ſubject or perſons wherein it is be altered; As it was the ſame, in kind, in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles time, in thoſe perſons in whom it was; as it was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards when it was in the univerſal Biſhop or Pope; For the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, in his own time, cals it <hi>the myſtery of iniquity,</hi> and ſo it was afterwards: So that though it may differ in degrees, or in reſpect of the perſons in whom it is, yet it remains the ſame in kind.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Now, according to the ſubject or perſons in whom it may be, this Eccleſiaſtical Magiſtracy, aſſumed by the Clergy, ſeems to be principally of four ſorts. For either it is 1 In the Pope, or univerſal Biſhop and his officers: Or, 2 In a company, or number of Biſhops and their officers: Or, 3 In a company of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113930:3"/>Miniſters and their officers: Or, 4 In every particular Miniſter, and his officers. The firſt, and laſt of theſe ſeem to differ but in this, that the firſt is univerſal, and the laſt particular; the other two alſo differ in names and degrees, not much indeed.</p>
            <p n="7">7. A Magiſtrate doth exerciſe a coercive power by rewards and puniſhments, ſo that he can ſay, <hi>do this good, and I will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect and defend thee, &amp;c.</hi> Or if thou do this evil, I wil inflict theſe and theſe puniſhments on thee. And ſuch a power the four ſorts of Clergymen, before mentioned, have aſſumed and exerciſed; that is, a power of Magiſtracy.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Neither doth the differences of the rewards or puniſhments inflicted by the Eccleſiaſtical Magiſtrates cauſe them to be no Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates: For amongſt thoſe which are granted, by all, to bee Magiſtrates, there be ſeveral forms of proceeding and cenſuring, yet all Magiſtrates.</p>
            <p n="9">9. <hi>Objection.</hi> The Eccleſiaſtical puniſhment is Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, or ſomething of that kind, concerning which a promiſe is made, <hi>That what is bound on earth ſhal be bound in heaven:</hi> So that it may ſeem to be a ſpiritual or divine puniſhment, and the releaſe upon repentance, a ſpiritual releaſe.</p>
            <p>Anſwer. <hi>So doubtleſſe is the ſentence of the Civil Magiſtrate, which he gives on earth, ratified in heaven, elſe it were in vain for him to ſit in judgment:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Even the ſentence of <hi>Pilate</hi> againſtour Saviaur Chriſt.</note> 
               <hi>Therefore they are ſaid to be in the place of God, and their ſentence the ſentence of God, even as the ſentence of Excommunication is; and the Malefactor juſtly ſentenced, by the Civil Magiſtrate, is ſo to apprehend it as the ſentence of God in heaven, extending not to his body only, but to his ſoul alſo, or the whole man, and that eternally without repentance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. So that Excommunication ſeems principally to be ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as a ſupplement, or in the defect of Chriſtian Magiſtracy; ſo as though it ſeem to be approved by <hi>Moſes,</hi> and it may be was in uſe among the Patriarks from <hi>Adams</hi> time; yet throughout the Old Teſtament whil'ſt the ordinary courſe of Magiſtracy was in force; though we find ſundry other puniſhments inflicted, we ſcarce find any mention of Excommunication, or any perſon Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate: In the New Teſtament we find it was in uſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Jews; but then the Jewiſh Magiſtracy was diſannul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, they being under the power and Magiſtracy of the <hi>Romans.</hi> Our Saviour alſo allows of it to his Diſciples; and the Apoſtle
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113930:4"/>
               <hi>Paul</hi> appoints it in the Churches of the <hi>Gentiles:</hi> But ſtil this was in the defect of Chriſtian Magiſtracy: For every Church is a Society, and no Society can wel ſtand without Magiſtracy, that is, without ſome puniſhment of evil doers, and encouragement for thoſe that do wel. Such a cours of Magiſtracy as is uſuall they might not ſet up, leſt they ſhovld ſeem Rebels to thoſe States and Kingdoms whereof they were ſubjects; It remaineth then that for any great offence obſtinatly perſiſted in, eſpecially ſcandalous, they might uſe this Magiſterial ſword of Excommunication; for this might be done without any the leaſt appearance of Rebellion or offending the Laws or Magiſtracy of thoſe Eſtates or Kingdoms under which they lived, whether they were <hi>Heathen</hi> or <hi>Jewiſh:</hi> but in Chriſtian States it is otherwiſe.</p>
            <p n="11">11. And here by the way we may obſerve the great Wiſdom and Providence of God, who is not the Author of diſſention and confuſion, but of peace and order, and his Ordinances do not thwart or hinder one another, but rather help and perfect one another; as in ordaining this Magiſterial power of Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication to ſupply the defect of an ordinary cours of Magiſtracy, he doth it ſo as that it ſhould no ways thwart, interfere, or hinder it, nor give any the leaſt juſt offence againſt it, or againſt Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates. And the like care for peace and order ought Chriſtians always to obſerve, that when there is no neceſſity of both, or that both cannot wel ſtand together, the one, namely, Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, muſt be laid aſide, and give place to the ordinary cours of Magiſtracy: But whil'ſt ſome would perſwade that God hath ſet up two kinds of Magiſtracy (not ſubordinate one to the other), and ſo two kinds of Magiſtrates, as Princes and their officers for the one, and Clergymen and their officers for the other; they have given occaſion of infinite troubles and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords in the Church, from time to time; and this ſeems to be the principal ground and occaſion of the continuance of our preſent troubles and dangers.</p>
            <p n="12">12. Beſides, if this power of Excommunication were neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily to be continued in its full vigor, yet it no where appears to belong to Clergymen: For as all Magiſterial power ariſeth Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally from the multitude or people over which it is ſet, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til Magiſtrates be ſet up, it remaineth in the people: ſo this power of Excommunication is attributed, or given to the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113930:4"/>or whole congregation under the name of the Church; and ſo it was moſt apt for thoſe times and occaſions for which it was ordained; and if it were to be confined into the hands of a few, ſurely then it ought to be confined into the hands of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, not of the Miniſters or Clergy, becauſe it is (as we have ſhewed) a Magiſterial power.</p>
            <p n="13">13. Thus then I ſay, that when there was no Chriſtian Magiſtrates nor ordinary Magiſterial power was or could be in the Church, our Saviour and his Apoſtles did ordain Excomunication to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead thereof, giving that power to each Church to excomunicate groſs and ſcandalous offenders, eſpecially when admonition, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof, ebuke private and publick would not reclaim them, which might ſufficiently, for the time, ſupply the want of an ordinary Magiſterial power: Not intending thereby to aboliſh the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Magiſterial power in government, nor to ſubjugate it to this extraordinary; nor to ſet up two Magiſterial powers in the Church (for Magiſtracy or Magiſterial power (as the Law) inclines to bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, &amp; the Church is not to be moſt in bondage of alother ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, but rather more free) but rather to ſupply the want of ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Magiſterial power, until it might take place, whe whole nations ſhould embrace the <hi>Chriſtian faith,</hi> and ſubmit <hi>themſelves</hi> to be ruled by <hi>chriſtian</hi> Laws &amp; Magiſtrates: and then the ordinary Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterial power, being more generally effectual for <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>unity,</hi> and the conſervation of great ſocieties <hi>(as whole Kingdoms, &amp;c.)</hi> ſhould take ful place: Neither then, it may be, was Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to be wholy aboliſhed, but to be exerciſed with fit limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions upon ſome ſpecial and extraordinary occaſions, <hi>for example ſake &amp;c.</hi> but no ways to the prejudice of the civil government, no more then it was in the firſt <hi>inſtitution</hi> as we have before obſerved</p>
            <p n="14">14. Yet we deny not that God hath ordained in the world and in his Church eſpecially, a twofold rule, or power, or authority, or government; and ſo alſo two kinds of Rulers or Governors: Even as the means of grace is twofold, namely, Legal and Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical, and the Legal helps to fit and prepare a man for the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelical: So in the Church, there is a twofold Rule or Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, namely, Magiſterial and Prophetical; and the Magiſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial helps to fit and prepare a man for the Prophetical. I ſay againe, as the nature of man is twofold, namely, ſpirituall and corporall, or of ſoul and body, or of the outward or inward man: So GOD hath ordained in nature,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113930:5"/>but eſpecially in his Church, a twofold rule, or government, ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to each of thoſe, namely, Prophetical, and Magiſterial; both jointly ſerve for regulating and perfecting the whole man; but the Prophetical eſpecially for the inner man, and the Magiſterial for the outer. The actions of the inner man (as to underſtand, to wil, to beleeve, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) cannot be wrought by a Magiſterial power, therefore the Lord hath ordained Inſtruction for the Underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, but eſpecially in the Church, the preaching of the Word to enlighten the underſtanding, to beget faith, through the operation of his Spirit, and ſo to work a free conformity or obedience of the whole man from inward principles. Again the outward man can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not directly and immediately be wrought upon by the preaching of the Word; therefore the Lord hath ordained a Magiſterial power, which by outward principles, as by rewards and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, may work it, at leaſt, to an outward conformity or obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; And to one of theſe all rule and government, and all Rulers and Governors are referred, namely, as they are either Propheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal or Magiſterial: And theſe do no ways interfere, thwart, on pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice the one the other, even when they are both extended to the utmoſt: And both theſe in a Church, or Chriſtian Commonwealth are to be exerciſed for the advancement of the Kingdom of Chriſt in the ſettling and propagation of true Chriſtian Religion, as their principal ſcope and end.</p>
            <p n="15">15. So that Miniſters are Rulers or Governors in the Church as well as Magiſtrates; yea they ſeem to have the more excellent Rule and Government, as more immediately, in a more excellent ſubject, yet their power is not coercive as that of the Magiſtrates, but perſwaſive &amp; Prophetical, ſuitable to the ſubject upon which they work, and ſo it is the moſt eminent work that is done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the ſons of men; working from inward principles (through the operation of the Spirit of God) a free and voluntary ſubjection and obedience to God: The Rule of Magiſtrates alſo tends to work ſubjection and obedience to God, but not ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately, nor cannot of it ſelf effect ſo much.</p>
            <p n="16">16. Yet it follows not that Miniſters are to be preferred in honor before all Magiſtrates, whoſe power may extend much fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, namely, over a greater number of men then that of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters which extends only to that Congregation over which he is; whereas the Magiſtrates may be over a whole City, or a
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113930:5"/>whole Kingdom. It is ſaid alſo <hi>God hath given honor to that part which wanted;</hi> namely, more external honor to the Magiſtracy; but if that alſo be added to the honor of the Miniſtry, it wil ſoon overtop all other honor among men: So that whereas the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>The Elders that rule well are worthy of double honor, eſpecially thoſe that labor in the Word &amp; Doctrine.</hi> It ſeems to be underſtood That of thoſe Elders, Officers, or Rulers whoſe power or authority extends no farther then that Congregation, the chiefe honor belongs to the Miniſter; which alſo may be more or leſſe, <hi>according to the gifts which God hath endued him with all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="17">17. Againſt what hath been before ſaid it may be objected, that Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates do often, to good purpoſe, joyn a Prophetical or perſwaſive power with their Magiſterial, or coercive power, laboring to bring men to a right order and obedience, by reaſons humane and divine without conſtraint, Why then may not Miniſters join a magiſterial and coercive with their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterial, or prophetical?</p>
            <p>Anſw. <hi>The Prophetical power, as we have ſaid, is more noble, more general, hath leſſe contraryty to any thing, works mord directly and immediately upon the more noble part of man, the ſoul, and ſo doth much advance and further the final ſcope and end of the Magiſtrates office without any contrarity to it;</hi> (Moſes <hi>ſaid,</hi> would God al the Lords people were Prophets, <hi>he would not ſay would they were all Magiſtrates, for that would have bred contrarity &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, which the other would not.</hi>) <hi>and therefore is more generally to be uſed by all Magistrates, and others. The Magisterial power is not ſo, wherewith if a Miniſter be inveſted, it doth ſomthing take him off from his proper office, which is more noble: Beſides, it doth ſomething darken it; for being clothed with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſterial power, it makes him rather a Legal, then Evangelical Miniſter, becaus his Magiſterial power is far more obvious to the apprehenſions of men then his Prophetical, which by this means is not apprehended, or very darkly and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly; as the ey being fixed upon ſome object very viſible; ſees not other things, or if it do, it is very obſcurely and confuſedly: Beſides it makes him of a ſpirit more Legal, leſſe Evangelical: Therefore our Savior himſelf, in the execution of his Prophetical office, laid aſide all Magiſterial power, which he would not have done if it had been profitable. So did the Apoſtles, ſo the Prophets of Old ordinarily; and ſo our Savior ſeems expreſly to command his Apoſtles and all Miniſters, in one place, where he ſaith,</hi> The Lords of the Gentiles bear rule o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them, and thoſe which are great exerciſe authority, &amp;c. but it ſhal not be ſo among you &amp;c. <hi>whereby he prohibits all Miniſters from the exerciſe of Magiſterial power: as if he ſhould ſay; thoſe which wil be great in the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of the Goſpel muſt be without all Magiſterial authority; He ſaith the Lords of the Gentiles, becauſ the Magiſtracy of the Iews was void, being under
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113930:6"/>the</hi> Romans; <hi>And ſo ſheweth whoſoever wil be great in the Miniſtry muſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe no authority as Magistrates do,</hi> He is to preach, convince, &amp;c. with all authority <hi>(that is, with all prophetical authority) but to have no Magiſterial or Coercive authority: And ſo he ſaith,</hi> Whoſoever wil be great among you, let him be your ſervant; &amp; whoſoever wil be chief among you, let him be your ſervant, <hi>now who is further from Magiſterial power then a ſervant.</hi> Even as the Son of man came not to be ſerved, but to ſerve, <hi>where he propoſeth (as elſwher) his own example, that he had exerciſed no Magiſterial power: And it hath been generally obſerved in</hi> England <hi>that when Magisterial power hath been conferred upon Miniſters, by making them Biſhops, they were the worſe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters ever after.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="18">18. This Eccleſiaſtical Magiſtracy of Clergymen, the Church hath had experience of in every kind: As <hi>in an Independent way; in a Preſbyterial way; in an Epiſcopal, or prelatical way; and in the way of an univerſal Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop or Pope.</hi> For whilſt the Churches were few, and they, for the moſt part, <hi>ſeparate in place, or far diſ-joined one from another,</hi> being under no Chriſtian <hi>Magiſtracy</hi> the Government, may ſeem to have been ſomething like that, which at preſent is called <hi>Independent:</hi> But the Churches grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more numerous and neerly conjoyned, they found it neceſſary for <hi>peace and unity</hi> they ſhould be Governed by the conſent of the <hi>Preſbytery,</hi> aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in ſome ſuch way as is now called the <hi>Preſbyterian Government.</hi> But afterwards finding many <hi>controverſies, ſciſms, and ſtrong oppoſitions amongst theſe and their followers,</hi> for their ſakes they thought it neceſſary to ſet <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops</hi> over them: afterwards finding much diſagreement among theſe Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and an aptneſſe in them to engage States and Kingdomes in their <hi>quarrels, to the ſtirring up of ſedition and great diſturbance,</hi> they yeelded to admit of an univerſal Biſhop over them all. And by this ladder hath the <hi>Pope aſcended to ſet himſelf above all humane powers:</hi> the firſt ſtep of which ladder, or rather the <hi>baſis or foundation on which it ſtands,</hi> ſeems to be this, <hi>that there is an Eccleſiaſtical Magiſtracy over the Church belonging to the Clergymen,</hi> and that <hi>jure divino;</hi> which being granted, the reſt wil follow, and can hardly be avoyded: And this, in every of theſe kinds of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>hath always grown prejudicial to the Church and Civil State; (hence have sprung the principal errors in the Church, which almoſt all make for the ambition and covetouſneſſe of the Clergy, an evident ſign that they have been the chief authors and promoters of them,</hi> this appears in the Church of <hi>Rome &amp;c.</hi>) which former times endeavored to redreſſe by altering the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from one form to another; but all in vain, becauſe they were all foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and all of them retained this falſe principle. And if the world ſhould continue ſo long as to make the like experience of them all again, <hi>though
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113930:6"/>they ſhould be ordered with as much care and circumspection as might be,</hi> yet doubtleſs they would prove as bad as before; nay, I am perſwaded, worſe; <hi>ſeeing we find not the ancient Independents, or thoſe which were likeſt to them, did ever, when they were at the worſt, hold any tenents, or uſe any practiſe, ſo dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous as theſe, which the Independents of theſe times do boldly and in a turbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent way bring in now upon their first riſing:</hi> (where ſhal we find <hi>more pride more uncharitableneſſe,</hi> they wil <hi>vilifie</hi> and <hi>unchriſtian the beſt Chriſtian,</hi> if he ſtand in their way, and ſeem not to regard the ruinating of <hi>Churches</hi> and <hi>Commonwealths,</hi> ſo they may ſet up themſelves, <hi>no, though it be the wombe that bare them, and the paps which they have ſucked?</hi>) What may we expect of them if they ſhould be <hi>authorized</hi> and <hi>continued.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="19">19. But the univerſal Biſhop being <hi>(by his foul train of Errors, in tract of time brought in)</hi> diſcovered to be the <hi>Antichrist,</hi> and his Government <hi>Antichriſtian,</hi> is now, through Gods mercy, exploded. The Biſhops alſo <hi>(the principal ſtirrers up of thoſe grievous troubles and dangers which are ſtil upon us)</hi> themſelves and their government is caſt off as <hi>Antichriſtian,</hi> for this cauſe eſpecially, <hi>becauſe they began of late to aſſume to themſelves an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limited and Independent power</hi> Jure divino; <hi>or an Independent Eccleſiaſticall Magiſtracy, and by that power brought inu ſundry Errors endangering Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and the Commonwealth.</hi> So that now the great oppoſition reſts, and is feared wil be between thoſe called <hi>Independents</hi> and <hi>Preſbyterians,</hi> and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially between the Miniſters on either ſide; the people (for the moſt part) oppoſing each other for their ſakes: And they (I mean the Miniſters) oppoſing each other for that which cannot appear to belong to either of them, namely, <hi>for an Eccleſiaſtical Magiſtracy over the Church,</hi> which e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven themſelues condemn in the two former <hi>Governments,</hi> namely, <hi>Papall</hi> and <hi>Epiſcopal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="20">20. We ſhal conclude; It is ſurely to be lamented that ſuch Miniſters in <hi>England,</hi> as ever ſince the Reformation, til of late, would have thought it ſufficient, <hi>if themſelves might have been freed from the dominion of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops,</hi> are now not content with that, <hi>except themſelves may exerciſe the like dominion over their brethren; and that by a law more unalterable than that of the Medes and Perſians,</hi> namely, <hi>jure divino;</hi> which the Biſhops never durſt challenge til of late, and which in them was a principall cauſe of ſtirring up the preſent troubles; and in theſe is a principall cauſe of the continuance of them, whilſt covering the miſtery by ſome of them inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, with ſpecious ſhews and plauſible pretences, they draw the common people, and many <hi>otherwiſe truely religious</hi> to their parſee. <hi>Oh that there were ſuch a minde in them as heretofore; and that they would in tonder com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion of the diſtracted eſtate of the Kingdome, content themſelves with ſuch
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113930:7"/>authority as heretofore, in the most happy and ſtouriſhing times of this Church and Commonwealth;</hi> namely, <hi>with preaching the Word, and adminiſtring the Sacraments, at leaſtwiſe for a time, til they could make it appear to the Honorable Parlament, ſome other power to belong unto them, and what that is, and how limited.</hi> And in the mean time ſuch offices and officers to be ſet in the <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> and <hi>in every particular Congregation, as were men of courage, fearing God, and hating covetonſneſſe, that might curb profaneſſe, and cheriſh piety, peace, and true Religion.</hi> And the Miniſters to have their <hi>claſſes, or meetings,</hi> for the ordaining and regulating of Miniſters, as other ſocieties have, <hi>according to the Word of God, and the approbation of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Parlament:</hi> Then might we hope to ſee peace again reſtored in our <hi>dear native Country,</hi> and <hi>true Religion ſettled with more power and purity then heretofore.</hi> For the ambition of ſome <hi>Clergymen</hi> in this very point (yet often, I confeſſe, obtaining the ſuffrages of <hi>pious and learned Chriſtians</hi> in their times) hath been the <hi>principal</hi> cauſe of errors and diſcords in the Church, whilſt the <hi>Pope</hi> would have ſuch a Power <hi>jure divino,</hi> by vertue whereof he did ſubjugate all other Powers (and of that nature it is where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever it is granted to ſubjugate in time all other powers): Of late the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops would challenge ſuch a power <hi>jure divino,</hi> but could not have, nor hold it ſo long as to ſubjugate other powers. Now Miniſters would have ſuch a power <hi>jure divino,</hi> and ſome as abſolute and Independent as any of the former: when no ſuch power of Ruling belongs to any of them <hi>jure divino,</hi> but only a Prophetical power of ruling the mind and conſcience by the Word of God; All other <hi>coercive and magiſterial power</hi> no ways be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to Miniſters <hi>jure divino,</hi> but to thoſe in place of Magiſtracy: I ſay if Miniſters would lay down this claim to an Eccleſlaſtical <hi>Magiſtracy,</hi> and content themſelves, as formerly, with their <hi>miniſterial and propheticall au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> (at leaſtwiſe for a time, till they could make it evidently to appear ſuch other power to belong unto them, and how limited) the occaſion of the preſent <hi>differences</hi> would be taken away, and <hi>unity, peace, and piety</hi> might be ſettled amongſt us, which is the ſcope here intended, and ought to bee the endeavor of every faithful <hi>Chriſtian.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
